<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Honesty's best policy, or, Penitence the sum of prudence being a brief discourse, in honour of the Right Honourable Anthony, Earl of Shaftsbury's humble acknowledgment and submission for his offences ... on the 25th of Febr. 1677 : together with the several proceedings of the said Right Honourable House ...</title>
            <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12561802</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12561802</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 326:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Honesty's best policy, or, Penitence the sum of prudence being a brief discourse, in honour of the Right Honourable Anthony, Earl of Shaftsbury's humble acknowledgment and submission for his offences ... on the 25th of Febr. 1677 : together with the several proceedings of the said Right Honourable House ...</title>
                  <author>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Marchamont Nedham. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63247:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>HONESTY's beſt POLICY; OR, <hi>Penitence the ſum of Prudence:</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Being a brief Diſcourſe, in honour of the Right Honourable <hi>Anthony</hi> Earl of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>'s humble Acknowledgment and Submiſſion for his Offences, upon his knees, at the Bar of the Houſe of Lords, on the 25th. of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1677.</head>
            <head type="sub">Together with the ſeveral Proceedings of the ſaid Right Honourable Houſe, in order to his Lordſhip's late Diſcharge from Impriſonment.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Publiſhed for prevention of falſe Copies, in ſo weighty a matter, and for the undecei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the People.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MIne eye was on divers particulars, when firſt I reſolved on the publication of theſe Papers,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To give a brief account of the Condition of this Kingdom, as it ſtood a little before the E. of S. began to offend.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of what nature his Lordſhip's Offences were when they began, and the dangerous Conſequences of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The high Wiſdom and Justice of His Majeſty and the Houſe of Peers, in doing right to Themſelves, and to the whole Body of Parliament, by preventing the Dangers then threatning Them, and the whole Government, in point of Safety.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The neceſſity of ſetting forth ſome Diſcourſe of this nature; together with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Houſe: that the winds of ſuch of His Majeſties Subjects as have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated and perverted through the Offences aforeſaid, and are not yet recovered, may be rectified from Principles and Doctrines, (both then, and as yet) deſtrustive to this most Noble Monarchy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Vanity and Fate, at all times, of Popularity and Faction in great Lords and Gentry; and of the Peoples being drawn in to a ſiding and driving of Parties among each other, to ſecond the pretences of Male-contented Great Ones, or the itchy humour of the leſſer Frie of Government-Tinkers. And that, in this juncture of Affairs, it is the utmoſt of all Treaſons to be Factious, when three Kingdoms are at ſtake in a Foreign War.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I conſidered alſo, that it can be no diſhonour to E. of S. but his glory (as it is of all true <hi>Penitents</hi>) to have his Repentance publiſhed, ſince it is his happineſs to ſurvive in publick, by the King's admirable Clemency, and remain a living Lecture to turn mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Tranſgreſſors from the Error of their ways. 'Tis ſaid in Holy Writ, <hi>He that turns many to Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> How happy then is his Lordſhip, that hath ſo fair an occaſion thus to improve his <hi>Penitence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. I obſerved alſo, There are a ſort of People, that not long ago were as buſie as Bees, to publiſh and diſperſe at large whatſoever they thought might be for the Honour and Advantage of his Lordſhip; only now they envy him the glory of the publication of this Ungrateful Wretches as they are, that a Noble Lord, after ſo much ſufferance of Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, for a Cauſe they profeſs'd to own, ſhould be ſo ill requited, as to have his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> ſmother'd (as much as in them lies.) for want of Air; Inſomuch, that either, no Copy of it is to be obtained from them, or but a clipt or counterfeit one! Therefore, to do Right to his Lordſhip, and that the deluded ſort of well-meaning People, may not be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63247:2"/>
deprived of the benefit of learning <hi>Repentance</hi> from his Lordſhip, with a ſight of their Errors, I reckon'd it a charitable publick-good work, to give them a ſight of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. <hi>Honi Soit Qui Mal y Penſe,</hi> Ill betide him that evil thinks: for I mean well in doing the buſineſs.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="transcripts_of_proceedings">
                        <head>The Papers following, being Tranſcripts of the Proceedings of the Houſe of Peers about this matter, from the 14th. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1677. to the 26th. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1677.</head>
                        <div type="date">
                           <head>Die Jovis, 14 Feb. 1677.</head>
                           <p>A Petition was preſented to the Houſe from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsburry,</hi> wherein he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmits himſelf to their Lordſhips pleaſure, and is ready to make Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment and Submiſſion according to their Directions, But in regard it did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to this Houſe; that his Lordſhip hath made his Acknowledgment to His Majeſty; after debate, the Queſtion being put, Whether this Petition ſhall now be rejected? It was Reſolved in the Affirmative.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="date">
                           <head>Die Mercurii 20 Feb. 1677.</head>
                           <p>A Petition from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was preſented to the Houſe, and read as followe. To the Right Honourable the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament Aſſembled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </p>
                           <q>
                              <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                                 <body>
                                    <div type="petition">
                                       <head>The humble Petition of <hi>Anthony</hi> Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
                                       </head>
                                       <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                                       <p>THat your Petitioner, on the 16th. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1676. was committed Priſoner to the Tower of <hi>London</hi> by your Lordſhips, becauſe he did not obey your Lordſhips Order; where he hath continued under cloſe Confinement, to the great decay of his Health, and danger of his Life, as well as prejudice of his Eſtate and Family.</p>
                                       <p>In all humble Obedience therefore unto your Lordſhips, he doth acknowledge that his endeavouring to maintain that this Parliament is Diſſolved, was an ill-adviſed Action; for which he humble begs the Pardon of the King's Majeſty, and of this moſt Honourable Houſe, and doth in all humble Duty and Obſervance to your Lordſhips, beſeech you to believe that he would not do any thing willingly to incur you Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
                                       <p>Wherefore your Petitioner, in all humble Duty and Obedience, both unto His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and your Lordſhips, hath made his humble Submiſſion and Acknowledgment in his moſt humble Petition unto the King's moſt Sacred Majeſty, and is ready to make his further Submiſſion and Acknowledgment to His Majeſty, and to this Honourable Houſe, according to the direction thereof. And he doth moſt humbly implore your Lordſhips, That you will be pleaſed to reſtore him unto your Favour, and diſcharge him from his Impriſonment.</p>
                                       <closer>
                                          <signed>And your Petitioner, as in Duty bound, ſhall, <hi>&amp;c. Shaftsbury.</hi>
                                          </signed>
                                       </closer>
                                    </div>
                                 </body>
                              </floatingText>
                           </q>
                           <p>This being read, the Lord Chancellor did let the Houſe know, That His Majeſty hath receiv'd a third Petition from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> more ſubmiſſive in form than the two firſt: But His Majeſty underſtanding that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to free himſelf from the Cenſure of this Houſe, by appealing to the <hi>King's Bench</hi> to have their Judgment thereupon, during the late Adjournment, doth not think fit as yet to ſignifie his pleaſure as to his Diſcharge, until this Houſe hath taken that matter into Conſideration.</p>
                           <p>After a long debate hereof, the Queſtion was propoſed, Whether an Addreſs ſhall be now made to His Majeſty to diſcharge the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> from his Impriſonment, upon his Petitions to His Majeſty, and to this Houſe?</p>
                           <p>Then the Queſtion being put, Whether this Queſtion ſhall be put? It was reſolved in the Negative.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63247:2"/>After this, the Houſe conſidered the matter of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s appealing from this Houſe to the <hi>King's Bench,</hi> to be releaſed by <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> And after debate, It is ordered, That the further debate of this buſineſs is adjourned till tomorrow mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, at which time the Records of the Court of <hi>King's Bench,</hi> touching the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s buſineſs there, ſhall be brought into this Houſe; the Judges are alſo to attend this Houſe.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="date">
                           <head>Die Jovis, 21 Feb. 1677.</head>
                           <p>This day the Houſe reſumed the debate concerning the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to free himſelf from his Commitment by this Houſe by a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> in the Court of <hi>King's Bench.</hi> And for the better knowledge of the mattere of Fact, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the <hi>King's Bench</hi> were produced; by which it did appear, That two Rules of that Court were obtained upon the motion of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Counſel, <hi>Trim Term,</hi> 1677, and the Returns thereupon were read; by which it did appear, That the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was committed the 16th. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1676. by this Houſe for a Contempt; And then the <hi>Remittitur</hi> of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> to the Tower was alſo read.</p>
                           <p>After this, a Petition of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was preſented to this Houſe, and read, wherein his Lordſhip took notice of an Order of this Houſe of the 20th. inſtant, for bringing the Records of the Court of <hi>King's Bench</hi> into this Houſe, concerning the matter of the <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> brought by him, that he takes himſelf to be greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and to have a right to be preſent and heard when any debate of any new matter againſt him be entred upon; That he cannot pretend, but that he may have erred for want of a Precedent to guide him; and being deprived of the benefit of Counſel, by reaſon of his cloſe Confinement, and being reſolved not to do any thing willingly which might in the leaſt offend His Majeſty, or their Lordſhips; He humbly takes this opportunity to give further evidence thereof, by caſting himſelf at their Lordſhips feet: And as he hath humbly begg'd the pardon of His Majeſty, ſo he begs alſo the pardon of this Houſe, for having offended them in any thing whatſoever.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>After a long debate thereof, the Houſe made theſe Reſolutions following.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Reſolved and declared, That it is a breach of the Priviledge of this Houſe, for any Lord Committed by the Houſe to bring a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> in any inferior Court, to free himſelf from that Impriſonment, during the Seſſion of Parliament.</p>
                           <p>Reſolved, That the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſhall have liberty to make his defence, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Reſolution and Declartion aforeſaid.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="date">
                           <head>Die Venerls 22 Feb. 1677.</head>
                           <p>The Houſe taking into Conſideration, when the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſhall come to this Houſe, and in what manner, and what ſhall be ſaid unto him; It is ordered, That he ſhall be brought to the Bar on <hi>Monday</hi> next, by the Conſtable of the <hi>Tower,</hi> or his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty; and then the Lord Chancellor ſhall ſay unto him to the ſame effect as his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was directed this day by the Houſe.</p>
                           <p>Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, That the Conſtable of His Majeſties Tower of <hi>London,</hi> be, and is hereby required, to bring <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> (now a Priſoner in the ſaid Tower, for his high Contempt committed againſt this Houſe) to the Bar on <hi>Monday</hi> the 25th. day of this inſtant <hi>February,</hi> at 10 in the forenoon; And this ſhall be a ſufficient Warrant on that behalf</p>
                           <trailer>To the Constable of His Majeſties Tower of <hi>London,</hi> his Deputy and Deputies, and every of them.</trailer>
                        </div>
                        <div type="date">
                           <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63247:3"/>
                           <head>Die Lunae, 25 Feb. 1677.</head>
                           <p>Then the Earl of <hi>Northampton,</hi> Conſtable of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> acquainted the Houſe, That, in obedience to their Lordſhips Order, he hath brought the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> who is without, ready to receive their Lordſhips Commands.</p>
                           <p>Upon this, the Lord Chancellor deſired to know the pleaſure of the Houſe, what he ſhall ſay to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> when he comes to the Bar; which words were written down, and being read, were approved of.</p>
                           <p>Then it was moved, That the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> might anſwer (as an Aggravation of his Offence) for ſome words which he ſpoke in the Court of <hi>King's Bench,</hi> when he appear'd upon his <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> which was conceived to be contrary to the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this Houſe, and that Witneſſes might be heard to prove the ſame before the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> be called to the Bar; but this was left to be as it is, until the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> had been called to the Bar, and his Anſwer received to what he ſtands already charged with.</p>
                           <p>The Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> being brought to the Bar, and having kneeled, the Lord Chancellor ſaid to him as was afore-directed by the Houſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>My Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The Lords have received a Petition from your Lordſhip, taking notice of the Contempt for which you are Committed by this Houſe; together with the Submiſſion to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Houſe: And while the Lords were taking into Conſideration that Petition, there were brought before this Houſe ſome Records of the</hi> King's Bench, <hi>whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, That your Lordſhip endeavoured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>to free your ſelf, by the Judgment of that inferiour Court, from the Cenſure of this. I am to acquaint your Lordſhip, that this Houſe has reſolved and declared, That for any Lord committed by this Houſe to bring an</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>in any inferiour Court, to free himſelf from that Commitment, during the Seſſion of Parliament, is a breach of the Priviledge of this Houſe: But withal, their Lordſhips have likewiſe reſolved, That it ſhall be permitted to your Lordſhip to make your full Defence, notwithſtanding the Reſolution and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aforeſaid. And therefore I am commanded to ask your Lordſhip what you are pleaſed to ſay for your ſelf upon the whole matter.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Whereupon the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> anſwered to this effect.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>My Lords,</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>I Have preſumed to offer two Petitions to this Honourable Houſe; the firſt your Lordſhip mentions, I do again here perſonally renew; humbly deſiring that I may be admitted to make that Submiſſion and Acknowledgment your Lordſhips were pleaſed to order: And that after a twelve months cloſe Impriſonment to a man of my Age and Infirmities, your Lordſhips would pardon the folly or unadviſedneſs of any of my Words or Actions. And as to my ſecond Petition, I moſt humbly thank your Lordſhips for acquainting me with the Reſolution and Declaration in that point; And though Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be in it ſelf very deſirable, and as my Phyſician (a very learned man) thought, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to the preſervation of my Life, yet I do profeſs to your Lordſhips, upon my Honour, That I would have periſh'd rather than have brought my <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> had I then apprehended, or been inform'd, that it had been a breach of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of this Honourable Houſe. It is my Duty, it is my Intereſt to ſupport your Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges; I ſhall never oppoſe them. My Lords, I do fully acquieſce in the Reſolution and Declaration of this Honourable Houſe; I go not about to juſtifie my ſelf, but caſt my ſelf at your Lordſhips feet, acknowledge my Error, and humbly beg your pardon, not only for having brought my <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> but for all other my Words and Actions that were in purſuance thereof, and proceeding from the ſame Error and Miſtake.</p>
                           <p>
                              <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63247:3"/>
                              <hi>Then his Lordſhip withdrew, and after ſome debate the Question was propoſed, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Witneſſes ſhall be now called in?</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The Queſtion being put, Whether this Queſtion ſhall be now put? It was reſolved in the Affirmative.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Then the Queſtion being put, Whether the Witneſſes ſhall be now called in? It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the Affirmative.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>There being a Paper made mention of in the Houſe, which was ſaid to be a Copy of what the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſaid in the <hi>King's Bench,</hi> but not permitted to be read; <hi>Robert Blaney</hi> was called in, and ſworn as a Witneſs; who being asked, whether he was preſent in the Court of <hi>King's Bench</hi> when the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> moved for his <hi>Habeas Corpus?</hi> And whether he heard all that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſaid there? He anſwered to this effect, That he was preſent in the <hi>King's Bench</hi> when the Earl of <hi>Shaftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> was there, and he heard the moſt part what his Lordſhip ſaid, but he cannot tell now what he ſaid; but he took ſome Notes, and that afternoon compared Notes with Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth,</hi> who alſo had taken Notes, and thereupon they perfected a Copy which he gave to the Lord Treaſurer.</p>
                           <p>He alſo ſays, That he cannot, for a thouſand worlds, ſay that he heard all that is in the Paper; nor he cannot now ſay what it was that he took, and what it was that he had from Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth,</hi> it being ſo long ſince, by reaſon of the many Interlineations made in the Paper, by comparing Notes with Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Then the ſaid</hi> Robert Blaney <hi>withdrew.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>After this, the Houſe agreed what acknowledgment the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſhould make at the Bar for his Offences: which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if his Lordſhip ſhould make, the Houſe would then Declare their Satisfaction in his Submiſſion and Acknowledgment; The Submiſſion is as followeth:</p>
                           <q>I <hi>Do acknowledge that my endeavouring to maintain that the Parliament is Diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, was an ill adviſed Action; for which I humbly beg the pardon of the Kings Majesty, and of this moſt Honourable Houſe. And I do alſo acknowledge, that my bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>in the Kings Bench, during this Seſſion, was a high Violation of Your Lordſhips priviledges, and a great Aggravation of my former Offence; for all which I likewiſe moſt humbly beg the pardon of this moſt Honourable Houſe.</hi>
                           </q>
                           <p>The Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was brought again to the Bar; and the Lord Chancellor told him, the Lords had prepared a particular Acknowledgment, which the Houſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he ſhould make, and read the ſame to him. And the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> made the ſaid Acknowledgment in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>I <hi>Do acknowledge, That my endeavouring to maintain that the Parliament is Diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, was an ill adviſed Action; for which I humbly beg the pardon of the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and of this moſt Honourable Houſe. And I do alſo acknowledge, that my bringing of an</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>in the Kings Bench during this Seſſion, was a high Violation of Your Lordſhips priviledges, and a great Aggravation of my former Offence; for all which, I likewiſe most humbly beg the pardon of this moſt Honourable Houſe.</hi>
                           </q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>His Lordſhip being again with-drawn.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>IT is Ordered, That the Lords with the white Staves now preſent, wait on His Majeſty, to give his Majeſty an Accompt, that this Houſe hath received Satisfaction from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> in the matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and the other Contempt, for which he ſtood impriſoned; and are humble Suitors to His Majeſty, That he would be pleaſed to diſcharge him from his Impriſonment; And that their Lordſhips do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Houſe to Morrow what they have done in this matter.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ordered, that the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>be in the mean time Remitted to the Tower<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                              </hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="date">
                           <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63247:4"/>
                           <head>Die Martis, 26 Feb. 1677.</head>
                           <p>The Lord Treaſurer Reported to the Houſe, That the Lords with the white Staves, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Order of this Houſe, have aſtended His Majeſty, to give His Majeſty an Accompt, that this Houſe hath received Satisfaction from the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> in the matter of the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and the other Contempt, for which he ſtood Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; and are humble ſuitors to His Mrjeſty, That he will be pleaſed to Diſcharge him from his Impriſonment; To which His Majeſty was pleaſed to give this Anſwer, That He will give Order for the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Diſcharge.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>NOw that you have peruſed the manner of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Deliverance out of the Tower, I ſhall, for Illuſtration of the Great Clemency of His Majeſty, and of the moſt Noble <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> purſue my purpoſe ſignified in the beginning, upon the enumerated <hi>Particulars,</hi> that the Government of this Monarchy may not loſe the benefit which may be improved out of an Accident of State ſo memorable, and ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be remembred, for Prevention of the like in future.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>I ſhall give an Account of the peaceful condition of this Kingdom a little before the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>began to offend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty before that time, had enjoyed as calm and quiet a Reign, as could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be imagined to have been had, in the midſt of a Nation ſo divided into various Opinions. A Reverence was paid to his Government by the Parliament <hi>Nemine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente;</hi> And it was a much more comfortable Seaſon for all His <hi>Great Officers,</hi> and others intruſted with the Management of Affairs under him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Publick Purſe</hi> was frankly open'd to Him upon all occaſions, without grumbling or delay; and the hearts of men were (in the beſt ſence) Simple, Open, and Chearful, in their Sentiments about all his Royal Purpoſes and Proceedings. Fears and Jealouſies were confined in the breaſts of thoſe only who never loved him, nor his Government; and thoſe Fears never ſhifted their Quarters among the Factions, to take up new ones in the <hi>Old Royal Party.</hi> The Houſe of <hi>Peers</hi> was as the <hi>Temple of Old;</hi> Not an <hi>Ax,</hi> nor a <hi>Hammer,</hi> no <hi>Noiſe</hi> was heard there; Nor were the <hi>Waters of the Sanctuary there trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</hi> nor any of the <hi>Veſſes</hi> of it expoſed to Scorn, nor any of its Utenſils, nor Offices, in danger of profanation: But all things went ſmoothly there.</p>
            <p>Next, As for the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> I may ſay much to the ſame purpoſe in the like ſtrain, of its wondrous Quiet and Calmneſs for Twelve Years together, before the time of the ſaid Earls Offences; its admirable harmony and conſent among themſelves, as well as its unparallel'd Loyalty, Liberality, and Duty to the King; the great aſſurance of mind they ſhewed all along about his Majeſties Royal Intentions towards the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Us againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and in the Enjoyment and Confirmation of our Legal <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties.</hi> What a mutual confidence was there betwixt King and Commons! So thoſe ſecret <hi>Snakes</hi> that were crept into the <hi>Common Hedge,</hi> durſt not ſo much as peep forth a head, to ſhew either their <hi>Factious Fork, Venom,</hi> or hiſſing, againſt the Wiſdom and Conduct of him or his Miniſters. And who, I pray you, was more Triumphantly tranſported to behold thoſe happy days, than this <hi>Penitent Earl?</hi> When being exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <hi>bright Orb of Chancellor,</hi> he moſt worthily proclaimed before both Houſes, <hi>Anno 1672. A publick Praiſe and Bleſſing to the Almighty, that he hath given us ſuch a King; That while War and Miſery rages in our Neighbour's Countries, our Garners are full, and no complaining in our Streets; So that a man can hardly know there is a War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let God be bleſſed, that he hath given this King ſignally the Hearts of his People, and most particularly of this Parliament; who in their Affections and Loyalty to their Prince, have exceeded all their Predeceſſors. A Parliament with whom the King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63247:4"/>
hath lived many years with all the Gareſſes of a happy Marriage. Has the Kings had a Concern? you have wedded it. Has his Majesty wanted Supplyes? you have readily, chearfully, and fully provided for them; you have relyed upon the Wiſdom and Conduct of His Majeſty in all His Affairs; So that you have never<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> attempted to exceed your Bounds, or to impoſe upon him,—On the other ſide, He hath been ſo tender of you, that He hath upon his own Revenue and Credit, endeavour'd to ſupport even Forein Wars, leſt he might become uneaſie to you, or burdenſome to His People. I can aſſure you, 'tis as impoſſible for the King to part with this Parliament, as it is for you to depart from that Loyalty, Affection, and Dutiful behaviour you have hitherto ſhewed towards him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us bleſs the King, for taking away all ur Fears, and leaving no room for Jealia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; for thoſe Aſſurances and Promiſes he hath made us. Let us bleſs God and the King our Religion is ſafe: That the Church of</hi> England <hi>is the Care of our Prince; and that Parliaments are ſafe. What more hath a good</hi> Engliſhman <hi>to ask, but that this King may long Reign; and that the Triple Alliance of King, Parliament and People may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be Diſſolved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What more eloquently and truly could have been ſaid, than was ſaid here in ſhort by our noble Penitent, to ſet forth the happy peaceful Eſtate and Condition of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? But note the time, it was in the year 1672<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that all was well; that the King had the hearts of his Parliament and People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that they were like Man and Wife; it was impoſſible to part or Diſſolve them: that the Parliament kept within their Bounds, meddled not with the Affairs of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> nor impoſed upon him, being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of his Wiſdom and Conduct; and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apt out of Tune with <hi>Fears and Jealouſies. Religion, Church, Parliaments, Properties, Liberties,</hi> all was ſafe in that <hi>Golden Year</hi> 72. And his Lordſhip having thus generouſly done the King all that Right, had reaſon to believe himſelf ſafe too.</p>
            <p>II. Having ſeen in what a peaceful happy ſtate all things were before the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Offending, 'tis meet that in the next place you ſhould ſee <hi>what the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences were when they began, the tendency and dangerous Conſequences of them; that others may be Converted, who through had Doctrine have been corrupted, and the like be avoided for the future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ingenious men uſe to have quick Motions, and Emotions of mind into Acts; and by this means oftentimes a ſudden Turn of their Minds and Fortunes, even to the toſſing of all things Topſie-turvy in a fit of ill humour. It was (you ſee) but in 72. That his Lordſhip had nothing to find fault with at Court; how it hapned preſently after this, that he was commanded to render up the Great Seal and Office of Chancellor, is not here to be diſcourſed, let it ſuſſice to know, That it was in the very next year 1673<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it was done, and his Lordſhip laid aſide, and 'tis no part of my buſineſs to meddle with the Faults that occaſioned it, becauſe my deſire is rather to cheriſh him in his Repentance, having often long'd to find him in ſo good a humour. It is for me only to give a few <hi>Obſervations</hi> about the Affairs which preceeded his Lordſhips departure from Court, while he was a prime Man in the Counſels of His Majeſty, which have ſince been made the Subject of many a loud Clamor by the <hi>Factious Party.</hi> Some <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> alſo I ſhall make of divers particulars, pointing out to you how, as ſoon as his Lordſhip went out, the World alſo it ſelf was troubled, and began to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> grow out of Order. Perhaps it hapned ſo, becauſe his Lordſhip went out of Office, his great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Conduct not being any longer at the Helm. A <hi>Poet</hi> of our own fancies, the Frame of the World to be bolted together with a <hi>ſmal Pin</hi> or two; if that be put out all falls to pieces: therefore when he brings in <hi>Catiline</hi> in the <hi>Third Act,</hi> in a great
<pb facs="tcp:63247:5"/>
chaſe, becauſe himſelf was rejected, and <hi>Cicero</hi> choſen <hi>Conſul,</hi> he makes him thus vent himſelf in a <hi>lofty Rant.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>Repulſe upon Repulſe?</head>
               <l>Oh that I could reach the Axel, where the Pins are,</l>
               <l>Which bolt this Frame, that I might pull them out,</l>
               <l>And pluck all into <hi>Chaos</hi> with my ſelf!</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So that you ſee, if but a <hi>Pin</hi> or ſo be out, all falls into Confuſion, if there be any Truth in <hi>Poetry.</hi> And it may be this was our Caſe, Who can tell? For, <hi>Poets</hi> have <hi>unlucky Hits</hi> many times, as well as <hi>Polititians.</hi> So have Hiſtorians too: For the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord-keeper,</hi> (or <hi>Recorder) of the Faction,</hi> I mean the Author of the <hi>New Directory for Petty Stateſ-men;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>The Account of the growth of Popery and Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> &amp;c. Reporteth to us, that the preſent <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> another <hi>Cicero,</hi> came in his Lordſhips Place before the end of 1673, as the former <hi>Cicero</hi> came into that which was aim'd at by <hi>Catiline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then the <hi>Golden times</hi> before, and in 72. being gon, the <hi>Iron age</hi> came on. But I muſt return where I left.</p>
            <p>As to my Obſervations about the Affairs preceeding his Lordſhips voidance from Court, I find the aforeſaid <hi>Recorder</hi> hath been very punctual to record them, and one may well think he is not like to ſay any thing in prejudice of his Lordſhip, becauſe I perceive in page 44. of his Pamphlet, he ſeems as if he would ſpeak like a Friend of his; and ſays, the Parliament having met the <hi>5th of February</hi> 1672. prepared an <hi>Act,</hi> by which the <hi>Papiſts were obliged to paſs through a new State-Purgatory, to become ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any publick Employment; and that the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury, <hi>then Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of</hi> England, <hi>Engaged ſo far in Defence of that Act, and of the</hi> Proteſtant Religion, <hi>that it coſt him his Place, and that it was upon this occaſion that he was laid aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord being now a <hi>Penitent,</hi> I would not upon any terms ſay ought in prejudice to him, by telling what the Occaſions and Cauſes were, that he was laid aſide. But appearing againſt <hi>Popery</hi> could not be the Cauſe, becauſe 'tis known there had been many years before, as great an out-cry among the <hi>Factious Party</hi> againſt Popery and Popiſh Counſellers, and yet it never appeared all along thoſe times, that ever his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip appeared againſt, or thought of any ſuch matter: for had there been any Cauſe for it, can we think that a Lord ſo Pious and Zealous of Religion would be guilty of concealing it, and have ſtood ſtill and look't on, while it grew up in the <hi>fair Sun-ſhine of all his good Offices?</hi> Sure, it could not be; and the <hi>Recorder-keeper,</hi> in this, inſtead of being a Friend to him, ſpeaks worſe than an Enemy. Beſides, you may remember, his Lordſhip himſelf in his fore-cited <hi>Speech to both Houſes</hi> gives him the lye, having therein told them and all the World on the ſame <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>February, 1672. That we were to bleſs God and the King, that the Church of</hi> England <hi>was then the Kings Care, and that our Religion was ſafe</hi> by conſequence then what needed his Lordſhips Defence of it by a <hi>New Act?</hi> Or how can it be thought the King would turn him out, for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending what His Majeſty Himſelf had under Care to preſerve? Theſe things do not hang together: And yet the <hi>Recorder,</hi> in his following words, in the ſame page, will needs become his Lordſhips Friend again and ſays, <hi>that his Lordſhips Defence of that Act,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>did not only cost him his Place, but was the Moving Cauſe of all thoſe Miſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures and obloquy, which His Lordſhip afterwards lay (ABOVE not) Under.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſay <hi>Dignum patellâ Operculum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a lucky Defender and Advocate is this for his Lordſhip. I mean rather an unlucky; That he, who in a Treaſonous Libellous Pamphlet, induſtriouſly now ſpred
<pb facs="tcp:63247:5"/>
and diſperſed into all hands about the Kingdom, to rail down both <hi>Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Royal Highneſs, all the High Officers of State,</hi> the <hi>Kings Privy Council,</hi> the <hi>Principal Secretaries,</hi> all the <hi>Judges,</hi> all other <hi>Officers of the Government,</hi> and the <hi>Court</hi> it ſelf, and then concludes all with a vile Jeering Careſs of His Majeſty Himſelf, ſhould in the ſame Book appear to be a Trumpeter of his Lordſhips Vindication and Praiſe. It looks ugly; but far be it from us, to think that there is any underſtanding betwixt him and the Author. 'Tis only his Lordſhips ill luck, that in divers other like Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets the <hi>Knaves</hi> have been ſo bold as to commend him: and who can help it?</p>
            <p>And yet on the other ſide, the <hi>Recorder,</hi> to ſerve the <hi>Faction,</hi> makes it part of his buſineſs to reckon up before 1673. while my Lord was intereſted in the Counſels at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> as many Faults (as he ſuppoſes) in the Government, as afterwards when his Lordſhip was gone. This is indeed a great Fault in Mr. Recorder, to let things drop that reflect upon ſo good a <hi>Patriot,</hi> as well as upon <hi>Whitehall.</hi> For, beſides <hi>Roman Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Slavery,</hi> he rails at Compliance with the <hi>French,</hi> War with the <hi>Hollander,</hi> breach of the <hi>Triple League, Shutting up the Exchequer;</hi> in the Counſels whereof before 73. my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was no ſtranger, and as forward as any man, and he reaped the benefit as cleverly. For they can tell at Sir <hi>Robert Viners,</hi> who in probability it was that knew of that of the Excequer, for aſmuch as Sir <hi>Robert<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Servants remembred afterwards, and ſmiled to think, that his Lordſhip a few days before the Shutting it up, was ſo wiſe as to call in 3 or 4000 <hi>l.</hi> out of their hands; for his Lordſhip is wont to do all things with very good Conſideration. Beſides, he hath been ſo boldly generous, as to juſtifie all the reſt of the foregoing Particulars, which are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at by the <hi>Recorder:</hi> For in his forementioned Speech on the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1672 to both Houſes as <hi>Chancellor,</hi> he told them, that as to the point of Poperies having been deſigned, it was a great Calumny [<hi>His Majeſty having ſo fully vindicated Himſelf from that Calumny concerning the Papiſts, that no reaſonable ſcruple can be made by any good man. And the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and all good Proteſtants, have reaſon to rejoyce in ſuch a Head, and ſuch a Defender. He was born and bred up in it: It was that his Father Dyed for. We all know how great Temptations and Offers he reſiſted abroad, when He was in His loweſt condition: and He thinks it the honour of His Reign, that He hopes to leave it to posterity in greater Lustre, and upon ſurer Grounds than our Anceſtors ever ſaw it.</hi>] Thoſe very words were a part of his Lordſhips <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peech in 72. and may ſerve for Anſwer to the Scandal of any deſign for <hi>Roman Idolatry.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, as to the <hi>Fear of Englands Slavery,</hi> you had his Word and Engagement in the laſt <hi>page</hi> of the Speech, <hi>That our Properties and Liberties are ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, as to the breach of the <hi>Triple League,</hi> the <hi>War</hi> enſuing with the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and compliance with the <hi>French,</hi> and the <hi>Black-heath</hi> Army, which are the Scandals mightily bandied about by the <hi>Recorder,</hi> and all the <hi>Factious ill willers</hi> to His Majeſty; hear alſo the Report of His Lordſhip, the <hi>good Patriot,</hi> while he was at the Helm, and in at all the moſt intimate Paſſages of the <hi>Cabinet,</hi> ſo that not a <hi>French Mouſe</hi> could an wagged there without his knowledge, to the hurt of <hi>England,</hi> and he juſtifies all the Counſels to the height concerning thoſe Matters. For in ſeveral pages of that Speech of his, <hi>viz.</hi> the 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, and 13. you will find things to have been thus; He takes off the imputation of <hi>that War,</hi> and of the breach of the <hi>Triple Alliance</hi> from the Counſels and Counſellers of the King, and chargeth it wholly upon the <hi>Hollanders</hi> themſelves, that they brake firſt, for that [<hi>beſides their denying His Majeſty the Honour of the Flag at Sea, they diſputed His Title to it in all the Courts of Chriſtendom, and made great Offers to the</hi> French <hi>King, if he would ſtand by them againſt Us. At this Seaſon, our King and his Miniſters had a hard time of it, and lay every day under new
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63247:6"/>
Obloquies. Sometimes they were repreſented as ſelling all to</hi> France <hi>for money to make War:</hi> Portſmouth, Plymouth <hi>and</hi> Hull, <hi>were to be given into the</hi> French <hi>hands for Caution. The next day, news came that</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Holland <hi>were agreed: Then the Obloquy was turned from Treachery to Folly; The Miniſters were now Feels, that ſome days before were thought Villains; For, if that Conjunction had taken effect, then</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>had been in a far worſe Caſe, becauſe the War had been turn'd upon Us. But both Kings knowing their own Intereſts, reſolved to joyn againſt them, who were the common Enemies of all Monarchies, and I may ſay, eſpecially to ours</hi>] Theſe are his own very words. And as he charges that <hi>War,</hi> and by conſequence the breach of the <hi>Triple League</hi> upon the <hi>Hollander,</hi> So he takes off the pretended Scandal of it from the King, and his Miniſters, and lays it upon the Parliament, alſo as well as the <hi>Dutch,</hi> ſaying in the ſame Speech openly to both Houſes [<hi>You judged aright, that at any Rate</hi> Delenda eſt Carthago, <hi>that</hi> Carthage <hi>was to be dectroyed;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>that the</hi> Dutch <hi>Government was to be brought down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore the King may well ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to you, 'Tis your War. He took his meaſures from you, and they were juſt and right Ones. And if after this you ſuffer them to get up again; let this be remembred, the States of</hi> Holland, <hi>are</hi> Englands <hi>eternal Enemy both by Intereſt and Inclination.</hi>] By theſe words our Factions <hi>Ill-willers</hi> may ſee, to, the Confuſion of all their Slanders againſt the King and his Miniſters, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels about the ſeveral particulars aforementioned, how fairly and prudently things were carried at <hi>Whitehall</hi> concerning them. Only one Point more is to be cleared, that is the <hi>Black-heath Army,</hi> a thing much babbled about as a Grand Bugbear by the ſame Generation, and a <hi>black</hi> Buſineſs to this day. <hi>My Lord</hi> will do this for us too. Thoſe few Forces which ſome will needs call an Army, during the <hi>Dutch War,</hi> were (if I forget not) to have been made about 6000<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to have been ſent to make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent upon ſome part of <hi>Holland,</hi> and were rendezvou'd at <hi>Black-heath</hi> for that deſign. O, but there was more in it! the Commander in chief was Monſieur <hi>Schomberg</hi> a <hi>French</hi> man. What then? But he war a Proteſtant alſo, and judged fit for that Work. In anſwer to this, let me mind you what the King himſelf ſaid in his <hi>Speech</hi> ſpoken the ſame day before the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> began his; His Majeſties words were: [<hi>There is one Jealouſie more that is malitiouſly ſpread abroad, and yet ſo weak and fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lous, that I once thought it not of moment enough to mention; but it may have gotten ſome ground with ſome well-minded People: And that is, that the Forces I have raiſed in this War, were deſigned to control Law and Property. I wiſh I had raiſed more Forces the laſt Summer; the want of them then convinces me, I muſt raiſe more. But I conclude with this Aſſurance to you; That I will preſerve the true Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Proteſtant Religion, and the Church, as it is now eſtabliſhed in this Kingdom, and that no mans property or Liberty ſhall be invaded:</hi>] You ſee the Jealouſies raiſed about thoſe Forces the King ſlights, as a <hi>frivolous piece of Malice,</hi> hardly worth men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But however gives all Aſſurance for Religion, Liberty and Property. And as for my <hi>Lord, he</hi> in <hi>page 13th</hi> of his <hi>Speech,</hi> calls it a <hi>Jealouſie</hi> fooliſhly ſpread abroad of the Frees the King had raiſed in that War: And he ſaith, <hi>It was ſo great an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the King, not to have raiſed more Forces at that time, that nothing but the true Reaſon, want of Mony, could have justified the defect in the number of thoſe Forces,</hi> And then as to the blame of their not doing the work that they had been raiſed for, his Lordſhip anſwers, <hi>that the preceeding Summer was a miracle of Storms and Tempeſts, ſuch as thereby ſecured their</hi> Eaſt India Ships, <hi>and protected their Sea coaſts from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent deſigned by thoſe Forces.</hi> And if you will not believe ſo Noble a <hi>Patriot</hi> as his Lordſhip about theſe matters, then go on to report and ſcatter your Scandals, till
<pb facs="tcp:63247:6"/>
your throats grow hoarſe and ſore with reporting, and become as incurable as your <hi>Faction.</hi> Nevertheleſs, with men not madly obſtinate, theſe Evidences ought to paſs, that there were no ſuch great Offences in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> nor in his Lordſhip neither, in the years before 1673.</p>
            <p>Now for the other part of my <hi>Obſervations</hi> in and after 1673 Divers great Offences grew up from time to time to put the World much out of Order; And verily theſe ſhould not be repeated, were it not of ſo high importance for Publick Service, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent falling into the like again, and to reſtore the minds of ſuch as are fallen.</p>
            <p>Never was more work done to put a Nation out of Order, in ſo little time as two or three years conſidering the good and happy condition it was in by his Lordſhips own Confeſſion; for from 73. to 1576: was no long ſpace, and by that time, his Lordſhip had taken up Lodgings in the <hi>Tower,</hi> It ſeems as if he beſtirred himſelf to purpoſe, and began betimes to offend, becauſe notice was taken preſently after a Court of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips behaviour, inſomuch that it is ſaid he was forbidden coming to Court; But to be even with them for this, and for other purpoſes, he took heart and hied as faſt as he could into the City, with Reſolution to become a Citizen, and trod the <hi>Exchange</hi> as a Merchant, and as conſtantly as any, being then to drive a great Trade in ſmall Wares of <hi>Popularity;</hi> how it came about you may gueſs, but as to a Common place for all People, there flockt the Factors of every <hi>Faction:</hi> Soon after this, Clubs and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of good Fellowſhip and Sedition were erected, and there all, and more than all the Infirmities of Court, and Errors of State, were Arraigned, and Condemned. The <hi>old Sore alſo,</hi> want of Trade, was rubbed, and the only Remedy reſolved on, <hi>viz.</hi> The removing of <hi>Evil Counſellers,</hi> and a crying down <hi>France, Miniſters of State,</hi> and <hi>French Penſioners, Arbitrarineſs,</hi> and <hi>Property<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> yea, all that was not at <hi>Court,</hi> was to be brought on the Stage, and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> too, and to be ſtript of their <hi>Lawn-ſleeves.</hi> Oracles like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were given out, to be delivered in Common Council at <hi>Guildhall</hi> by Mr. <hi>Jenks</hi> and his fellow <hi>Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſecres,</hi> and Orders iſſued out for a general Muſter of <hi>Grievances</hi> againſt the Seſſion of Parliament; beſides many a coſtly Dinner, and deep Potations, for the putting as many Members as they could out of their Senſes. There the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances were firſt ſet on Foot, to Inſtitute <hi>Offices of Intelligence,</hi> to <hi>coyn News</hi> for the <hi>Coffee-houſes;</hi> and an <hi>Academy</hi> for inventing <hi>Seditious</hi> and <hi>Treaſonable Pamphlets,</hi> with Directions how to Print and Spread them, to edifie both City and Kingdom into an Oblivion of their Allegiance, and a belief of meere Inventions; that ſo they might be rendred tractable towards any deſign of their <hi>Factious Leaders,</hi> and for the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a diligent Correſpondence of their <hi>Countrey-Agents,</hi> with the ſupream Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the <hi>Directors</hi> at <hi>London.</hi> Theſe were the bleſſed fruits of the Years 1674. and 76. I am far from charging his Lordſhip with any of them; but I may only obſerve, that all theſe beginnings of Diſorder follow'd his Lordſhips laying aſide at Court, and were the unhappy <hi>Conſequents</hi> in time of his Courtſhip in the City.</p>
            <p>After a while, ill humours, like <hi>ill Weeds,</hi> grew ſo faſt, that now they began to think themſelves both powerful and skilful enough to <hi>play a Prize</hi> in Parliament: and therefore ſeeing the Memorable Seſſion of <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1675. was at hand, they provided their pranks ſo to play, that the Parliament ſhould not be in Condition to do any work, but both Houſes only embroil one another with hard Speeches, and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes about Priviledges,</hi> &amp;c. and thereby being in no capacity to make diſpatch of Publick Buſineſs, be rendred altogether impracticable and unuſeful to the King and Kingdoms preſſing Occaſions. This device was driven high, and with heat for an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical blowing up of this Parliament, becauſe the <hi>But-end</hi> of it was to induce upon the King a neceſſity of calling a <hi>new One:</hi> in this Point entred all the Crafts-Maſters of
<pb facs="tcp:63247:7"/>
every <hi>Male-contented Party,</hi> as the grand <hi>Medium</hi> wherein they could agree againſt the preſent Eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Court,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>overnment both of Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> becauſe each Party having prepared men to ſerve it ſelf, by new Elections, doubted not but ſo plauſible a Plea as a <hi>New</hi> Parliament, would eaſily take place and afford eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one the advantages they hoped for by a Change. His Majeſty and His Conncil, and the Parliament, ſoon ſmelt out the deſperate meaning of this <hi>Privy Conſpiracy</hi> under cover of ſo <hi>publick a Plea,</hi> and the <hi>Faction</hi> was ſoon made to underſtand, that their <hi>Plot</hi> was underſtood; and that Crafty <hi>Tricks,</hi> with Loud <hi>Popular</hi> Clamors, and Long Speeches of their Correſpondents in Parliament, with other Machinations under the Sacred ſhelter and Claim of <hi>Free ſpeaking,</hi> and Priviledge, was no honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> way to bring on <hi>New Parliaments;</hi> the Law having left it wholly to the Judgment and Power of the King, who hath at all times had a willingneſs to call one, as ſoon as the Publick work lying before this Parliament can be finiſhed, and the Heats, high Cants, and Traiterous deſigns of Factions to make an uproar, can be evaporated.</p>
            <p>The working of all theſe Evils, was plainly ſeen ſo ſoon as in this <hi>April-Seſſion</hi> of 75. to be the wretched effect of thoſe Principles and Doctrines of State, which by the care of the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> had been moſt induſtriouſly ſpread in Prints and otherwiſe, for Poyſoning the Opinion of City and Countrey about the King and His Parliament, and the Government, all expoſed for a ſubverſion.</p>
            <p>Some Noble Lords, at that Seaſon, reflecting on their own Allegiance, and Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to prevent this, brought into the <hi>Houſe of Peers</hi> a Bill, in which was that <hi>Oath</hi> ſo much clamour'd at, called the <hi>Oath of Teſt</hi> or Tryal; conceiving it would be a good ſecurity to Church and State, if men thereby renewed their Allegiance. It ſeems the <hi>Plot,</hi> after the Rate of 1641. was ſo forward, that the <hi>Masters</hi> of it were touched to the quick, and feared this <hi>Oath</hi> would touch too home alſo upon their <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> who by it were to ſwear down the Principles and Doctrines of 41. which were now again to be made uſe of, ſuch as allowed of taking <hi>Arms againſt the King</hi> upon Parliamentary pretences, and <hi>by His Authority againſt His Perſon,</hi> and of <hi>making Alterations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Him, in Church and State.</hi>—If the Book called <hi>A Letter from a Perſon of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Friend in the Countrey,</hi> publiſhed this year 75. be of any Credit, it hath theſe words in <hi>page</hi> 9. That the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was the man in the Houſe, <hi>that opened at large the Miſchievous and ill Deſigns (as he calls it) and Conſequences of the Bill,</hi> and convinced many other Lords into a humour of <hi>Proteſting</hi> againſt the <hi>Bill.</hi> Now the deſign was <hi>bare-faced;</hi> And becauſe the <hi>Church</hi> was to have been alter'd as well as <hi>State,</hi> therefore, he who will believe that Book, may if he pleaſe, when as in 20. and 21. and 22 <hi>pages,</hi> it ſaith, That his Lordſhip ſpake things in diſgrace of thoſe old repoſitories of the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> the <hi>Homilies</hi> and the <hi>Canons.</hi> And I am ſure the ſame Book, which condemned theſe, and vilified the <hi>Biſhops</hi> too, beſtows very high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of his Lordſhips Parts, Pains, and Labour about theſe matters: which, to the praiſe of his, and ſome other mens <hi>Lungs,</hi> took up the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of Sixteen or Seventeen whole days together, the Houſe ſitting many times till Eight or Nine a clock at night, and ſometimes till midnight. However, they could not ſave the <hi>Book</hi> which makes report of this Noble Prize, from being, by Order of the <hi>Peers,</hi> burnt by the hand of the <hi>Hangman.</hi> And indeed it well deſerved ſo, becauſe it charged the main ſtreſs of the Debate upon the ſhoulders of his Lordſhip; though the <hi>Author</hi> wrote as if he had been his Friend, by reaſon of the immoderate Praiſes that he loads him with in divers places. 'Tis an unhappy thing, and looks ill, that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhould have ſuch dangerous Friends as deſerve Execution by the <hi>Hangman:</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:63247:7"/>
what praiſe ſoever the fore-going <hi>Author</hi> may have fallen ſhort in, another <hi>Author</hi> endeavours to make up, who ſeems a Friend too of his Lordſhip, by an exceſs of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him for the oppoſing of that Oath; as may be ſeen in <hi>pages</hi> 17, 58, 59, 69. and 61, 62 of that <hi>Author,</hi> whom a little before we named the <hi>Record-Keeper,</hi> or <hi>Recorder</hi> of the <hi>Faction;</hi> that is more plainly, the Author of that moſt Villainous Book, Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lep, <hi>An Account, &amp;c.</hi> in the 61 <hi>page,</hi> whereof are theſe very words [<hi>It might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious where all of them did ſo excillently well, to attribute more to any one of thoſe Lords than to another, unleſs, becauſe the Duke of</hi> Buckingham <hi>and the Earl of</hi> Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury <hi>have been the more reproached for this brave Action, it being requiſite by a double proportion of praiſe, to ſet them two on equal terms with the beſt of their Companions in Honour</hi>] And in <hi>page</hi> 62. He glorieth in theſe words concern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng the Iſſue of theſe doings: [<hi>That by this means the Teſt Dyed, and the Matter in concluſion was ſo Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded betwixt this buſineſs, and the buſineſs of Dr.</hi> Shirly, <hi>and Sir</hi> John Fagg, <hi>that any longer converſe between the two Houſes grew impracticable; ſo that His Majeſty was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to Prorogue them till the</hi> 13th <hi>of</hi> October, 1675. following] Let the World judge then to what height of Crime ſuch mens behaviour doth tend, when it muſt puzzle the moſt exquiſite <hi>Politician</hi> to diſtinguiſh in point of Treaſon, betwixt a <hi>Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator</hi> and a <hi>Subverter</hi> of the Meetings of Parliament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſo you have ſeen what Friends his Lordſhip hath, and if their Prints are to be believed, you ſee what he did, and how he did, and how he beſtirred himſelf during that <hi>April-Seſſion</hi> of the year 1675</p>
            <p>Now we paſs on to <hi>October-Seſſion</hi> of the ſame year; and in this it will appear, how the work of publick Diſturbance, and of <hi>Fruſtrating</hi> this Meeting of Parliament like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe proceeded; for, it alſo came to nothing: but by whoſe means, let the <hi>Reader</hi> judge by what followeth in ſhort.</p>
            <p>The Parliament being met, the firſt Artifice of ſome was, to ſet on Foot again the late <hi>Quarrel</hi> betwixt both Houſes about their Priviledges. In which <hi>Maſter-piece,</hi> if we may credit a <hi>Speech</hi> Printed in the name of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> his Lordſhip act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a principal part, and it was improved from being a <hi>private Cauſe</hi> between <hi>Shirly</hi> and <hi>Fagg,</hi> to become a cauſe of too much concern to the King, the whole Parliament, and Kingdom. Therefore divers Lords argued in their Houſe to lay aſide for a while that Cauſe, as a matter that would revive their Conteſt with the Commons: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hinder the Kingdoms buſineſs of preparing a Navy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and other preſſing Affairs and Occaſions: and ſo moſt of the Lords ſpake for adjourning that Cauſe for ſix weeks. But, ſaith the <hi>printed Speech,</hi> in my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s name; Take heed what you do, and argued theſe Particulars following:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That then the</hi> Money-Bill <hi>for the King to build Ships would be paſſed.</hi> Oh take heed of that; for though in a another part of the Speech an Out-cry be made of the Crown of the <hi>French</hi> King, yet no Money ought to be had to prepare by Sea or Land againſt him. This way of arguing ſuits well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to lay</hi> Shirly <hi>aſide</hi> would be to alter the <hi>Conſtitution of the Government.</hi> Well argued again. <hi>That no Prince ever govern'd without a Nobility,</hi> or any Army. <hi>If he will not have one, he muſt have t'other.</hi> Well done to inſiunate, as if the King meant an Army Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the King is King by Law, and by the ſame Law that a poor man enjoys his Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi> I thought he had been King by Inheritance; that is, according to Law, and the fundamental Law of the Kingdom ſuppoſes that no Law is able to alter it; Elſe the Heir of the Crown may hap to be without either Palace, or Cottage, by I know not what Law. <hi>That a King governing by an Army, without His Parliament, is a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that his Lordſhip owns not, is not obliged to, nor was born under.</hi> This is to ſet
<pb facs="tcp:63247:8"/>
up a <hi>King of Straw,</hi> and place him in the head of an Imaginary Army, and then rout him with an infinuating Slander.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he cannot find that ever the Jeſuits or Popiſh Clergy, only ſome of our Epiſcopal Clergy, owned Monarchy to be of Divine Right.</hi> Then the Epiſcopal are the beſt Subjects. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterian may ſuit with the other, being the ſame by Principle, a ſort of <hi>Proteſtant Jeſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to ſay this Family are our Kings, and this Partioular Frame of Government is our lawful Conſtitution, and obligeth us, is owing only to the particular Laws of our Countrey.</hi> Well urged in Print: here is ſcope enough left both for <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Frame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterations</hi> by particular Laws. All our wiſe men have doted till now, they dream't that the General Fundamental Law of the Kingdom had held both <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Frame</hi> ſo together, that they are unalterable by any particular Law whatſoever.</p>
            <p>What think ye now? hath not that man a notable skrew in his Brains, that could draw all theſe brave Points out of the Caſe of Dr. <hi>Shirly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, a ſhift was made with <hi>Shirly</hi>'s buſineſs to make long Speeches, and ſo inflame the Reckoning betwixt both Houſes, that no publick buſineſs being to be done, this <hi>Seſſion</hi> alſo was made as unſerviceable as divers foregoing Seſſions had been; and the time was drull'd but till the <hi>20th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1675. And then the main In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment for the Deſtruction, otherwiſe called a Diſſolution, of this Parliament came to light, back't with ſuch Reaſons in writing, afterwards Printed, with the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s and ſome other Names to them, which no Lord could have ſo readily and luckily penn'd, as one that formerly had an Acquaintaince with the Levellers; the Arguments being all of a piece with theirs in the former times of Reformation; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that His Majeſty finding no good to be done, was forced, for meer ſhame of our Nation, and to hide it, to put an end to this <hi>Seſſion</hi> alſo, the <hi>22th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1675. And that men might have time enough to diſcover their own Errors, He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued them to the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> 1676. In the mean time, no Money having been raiſed, as the King earneſtly had deſired of them for building of Ships, and other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations for War; but ſet the Saddle upon the right Horſe, or lay the Brat at the right door, and rail not at them for not doing what was contrived, and made impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to do, by with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>holding Money from them that ſhould have done it: which lamed them and the whole Nation in ſuch manner, that they could not make one ſtep towards it. And this is the true Reaſon why we loſt ſo much time, and are ſo behind hand and backward at this day.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, the much long'd for <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1676. being come, the King, as if He had forgotten all Faults, and Injuries of the former <hi>Seſſion,</hi> (ſuch is His marvailous Clemency and Patience) opened this with a Speech of a moſt obliging Nature, ſuch a one as was a wonder, Conſidering what Provocations had been put upon Him, and His Government in the interval of the <hi>Seſſion,</hi> by the many moſt pernicious Books and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets which had been ſpread by the <hi>Faction</hi> into all parts, to inflame and prepare the People for new Commotions (if it might be) to diſturb Him this <hi>Seſſion</hi> alſo, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Parliament; in which work of <hi>Diſſolution</hi> the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> at the Houſes ſitting (you know) was prime man in appearing, to the utmoſt of his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>As for the King, He in His Speech to both Houſes, in hope to reconcile all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, breath'd forth nothing but ſweetneſs, Kindneſs, and high Reaſon.—He told them, <hi>That after a long Proregation, He had given them the Opportunity to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Misfortunts of the former Seſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63247:8"/>
               <hi>That if they fell into the like Differences now again, which ſome men had ſo unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily managed and improved betweenn them, it would be enough to leave them without all excuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That His Majeſty Himſelf was reſolved it ſhould not be his fault, if they were nit made happy by their Conſultations in Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he came prepared to ſatisfie them in all things, for ſecuring our Proteſtant Church and Religion, that may be reaſonably asked, or can conſist with Chriſtian Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he was ready to do all things that might gratifie them in the further ſecuring of</hi> Liberty <hi>and</hi> Property.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That then he leaves all the World to judge, who is moſt for Arbitrary Government, they that foment ſuch Differences as tend to diſſolve all Parliaments, or he that would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve This, and all Parliaments from being made uſeleſs by ſuch Diſcentions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if the good ends of Government, and the neceſſaries of it, happen to be further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, he called God and men to witneſs that day, that the misfortunes of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment ſhall not lie at his Door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which excellent particulars, my Lord Chancellor in his Speech added many more, too large to repeat here; only one I muſt remember: <hi>That it would be ſomewhat ſtrange, and without all example in ſtory, that a Nation ſhould be twice ruined, twice undone, by the ſelf-ſame way and means, the ſame Fears and Jealouſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all this was but <hi>Surdo canere;</hi> what was to be done was before-hand reſolved on; The <hi>Actors</hi> entred in the Houſe of Peers, and the <hi>Tragy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Comaedy</hi> began thus, as the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder</hi> of <hi>the account of the growth of Popery,</hi> &amp;c. (pages 71, 72.) preſents it, (which Book, being now in the hands of the Houſe of Peers, deſerves their moſt ſevere Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;) For he ſaith, <hi>The Duke of</hi> B. (<hi>one who uſually ſays what he thinks) argued with great ſtrength of reaſon, that this Prorogation was</hi> null, <hi>and this Parliament conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Diſſolved.</hi> But other Lords moved, <hi>That for this the Duke ought to be called to the Bar. So that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>had opportunity to appear with ſuch extraordinary vigour, in what concerned both the Duke of</hi> B'<hi>s Perſon and Propoſal, that as the Duke of</hi> B. <hi>might have ſtood ſingle in any rational Conteſt, ſo the Earl of</hi> Shaftsbury <hi>was more properly another Principal, rather than his Second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a virulent Scribe is this <hi>Recorder,</hi> that an ill Conteſt cannot ariſe in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but he ſtill brings in my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> as a main man, a Beginner, or a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of it! If he was ſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he greater then ought to be his Lordſhips <hi>Repentance</hi> all the days of his Life; otherwiſe, though he hath done it at the <hi>Lords Bar,</hi> there is yet a Superiour Bar hereafter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he muſt one day give an Account to. In the mean while, both he and the <hi>Duke,</hi> being <hi>Penitents profeſs'd,</hi> it ſounds not well that this <hi>Recorder</hi> ſhould now be the Trumpet of their Praiſes; For, we would fain believe they are real, and mean to give him no more the like occaſion by <hi>Parliament-pelting;</hi> nor to count him in the number of their Friends hereafter.</p>
            <p>Whoever he was that publiſhed the <hi>Debates and Arguments</hi> that had been delivered in the Houſe of <hi>Peers</hi> formerly <hi>for Diſſolving the Parliament,</hi> will find it confeſſed in that print, that it was a parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <hi>Deſign,</hi> it having been boaſted by the Deſigners, <hi>That they had a Party of Members in the Commons Houſe, whoſe buſineſs it was to ſecond the Diſputing Lords, by carrying the Differences in both Houſes to the greateſt height, that by this means they might be rid of this Parliament by Diſſolution:</hi> which is a new way of <hi>Blowing up</hi> a Parliament, that calls aloud for <hi>Repentance;</hi> and God grant that in our days, neither the ſame, nor the like <hi>Tricks of State,</hi> may be brought upon the Stage any more.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63247:9"/>When this would not do, then for my Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and the reſt that joyn'd with him in Argument, to argue from the <hi>Fifteen Months<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prorogation</hi> of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it was conſequentially <hi>Diſſolv'd</hi> and <hi>Null,</hi> was ſuch a <hi>Jigg</hi> to be brought in among wiſe men, as never was ſeen in any Age, nor could have been ſeen in any but in this Age of Wonders, and wondrous boldneſs with Kings.—The vanity of it was ſufficiently refuted by many Noble Lords in the Houſe, and afterwards in Print, by a private hand, where the whole Deſign and Drift of it was explained to the People.</p>
            <p>But that which is worth all, is his Lordſhips <hi>own Repentance;</hi> for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> knew him to be of ſo <hi>clear a Wit,</hi> that when the angry Clouds of <hi>Faction,</hi> and Hearts of <hi>Diſpute</hi> ſhould be over, his piercing Judgment would quickly eſpy that he had been out of the way; and that ſeeing the <hi>Tower</hi> agreed not with his Conſtitution (as was acknowledged in his <hi>Petition</hi> to the <hi>Houſe</hi>) it was his beſt way to return to the <hi>Bar,</hi> and there to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and beg Mercy-of His Majeſty and the <hi>Right Honourable Houſe,</hi> and from that moſt Noble Theatre Preach <hi>Repentance</hi> to all that had been perverted by his Doctrine and Example. Which he having done, what remains, but that he may ſpend the reſt of his days with the Bleſſing of a <hi>Convert,</hi> the Comfort of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and in contemplating alſo the many <hi>Pardons</hi> which from time to time our moſt Gracious King hath beſtowed upon him?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
